<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The reformed Catholicque, against the deformed Iesuite. Or A discovering of the trecherie of the Iesuites against the reformed churches of France, and other partes. Written by an inhabitant of Rochill, 1621</title>
            <author>Inhabitant of Rochill.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18207</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4830.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109166</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844816</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844816</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9662</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18207)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9662)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1627:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The reformed Catholicque, against the deformed Iesuite. Or A discovering of the trecherie of the Iesuites against the reformed churches of France, and other partes. Written by an inhabitant of Rochill, 1621</title>
                  <author>Inhabitant of Rochill.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Netherlands? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Publication date and place of publication conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9662:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9662:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE REFORMED CATHOLICQVE, Againſt the <hi>Deformed Ieſuite.</hi> OR A DISCOVERING Of the trecherie of the Ieſuites Againſt the Reformed Churches of FRANCE, And other partes.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Marke 13.12.13.</bibl>
               <p>The Brother ſhall betray the Brother to the death, and the Father the Sonne, and Children ſhal riſe up againſt their Parents, and ſhall cauſe them to be put to death.</p>
               <p>And you ſhalbe hated of all men for my names ſake, but he that ſhall endure unto the ende, the ſame ſhalbe ſaved.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by an Inhabitant of Rochill</hi> / 1621.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9662:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:9662:2"/>
            <head>THE REFORMED CATHOLICQVE, Againſt the <hi>Deformed Ieſuite.</hi> OR A DISCOVERING Of the trecherie of the Ieſuites Againſt the Reformed Churches of FRANCE, And other partes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou ſhalbe hated of Kings / and the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt perſonages of the World / ſhall ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre you. It is a Propheſie that is moſt true / and what this daye wee ſee and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold to be common amongſt us / wee are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred of the people / as the moſt abhominable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the world / diſpiſed both of great and litle / and
<pb facs="tcp:9662:3"/>
gennerally expoſed unto the opprobries / indignities / and indiſcreet inſolencies of mutinous Companions / and contemners of the Law of God / only for our Religion / bycauſe wee ſerve God in Spirit and truth and bycauſe wee wil not ſubmit ourſelves under the yoake of the beaſt. The Iew / the Turke / the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan / and the Moore that know not God / are not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the World as wee are / and whie? bycauſe wee art of the Religion bycauſe wee ſerve God / and will not follow the ſonne of perdition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>FRANCE</hi> at this tyme is full fraughted even in the furtheſt Provinces and partes thereof with our miſeries Shadowes deplore and lament our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions in the midle of the Reformed churches that are furtheſt diſtant from the realme / pitie hath made knowne the deſolation of our holy communetie / throughout all the World / are the good ſervants of God in all parts ſight / deploring the pitiefull diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der / and ſorrowfull abuſe that is now practiſed in the church of God prophaning his holy Howſe / deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Temple / ſpoyling his inheritance / expoſing the flocke of God / to the rage of Wolves / and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veing them for a pray to hongry Drons / who in diſpight of God fell them ſelves and their cruell harts with the ſubſtance of his deare flocke / and which is more ſenſible / and the full accompliſhement of our greefes / thoſe that ought to help us / are they that committ moſt oppreſſions and extortions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us / who moſt unjuſtly ſuſtaine / maintaine / and entertaine thoſe / that doe all theſe miſchiefes unto us / inciting them to doe it / and under pretence of doing us Iuſtice / animate them againſt us / and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:9662:3"/>
draw them to a plublicke rebellion / thereby to wrong and make us the authors of all theſe ſeditions. Wee are dumb / like ſheep led to the ſlaughter. If wee make our complaintes / and implore the ſupport and ayde of thoſe that ought to maintaine us / wee are accuſed to be mutinous and ſeditious / wee are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to priſon / and our innocencie / without any ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification is condemned criminall / and turbulent to the common peace. Oh moſt extreame Tyranie / and incomparable iniquitie. But alas! it is propheſied and forſhowne by the Lord.</p>
            <p>They are not content to have taken Bearn from no / to have polluted our Temples / to have forced our conſciences / to have prohibited the exerciſe of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion unto us in thoſe parts / to have taken our goods from us / to have violated our priviledges / to have compelled us to entertaine and maintaine our ennemyes with that ſmale portion that is left us. The Wolf takes the Sheep / and devoures it / the Theef takes a mans purſe and his mony from him / and you take our goods and bodies both / but you can not hurt our ſoules. Wee muſt give the juyce of our travels unto perfidious hipocrytes / to ſecret Traitors / or to venimous ſerpents to nouriſhe them to make warre upon us / what ſaye I? To nouriſhe them / when they have as great revenewes as Kings alas! what impietie is? they rumate us / but not to enriche the Crowne of France / but rather to laye it open to an invaſion. Theſe Ieſuiticall conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors without forraine ennemyes / will rule the regale Sceptre / if they attaine to the intents of their ſubtill and diabolicall inventions / which they have
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:9662:4"/>
allredy begon / and ſeing that they know that they can rule both the harts and bodyes of our Kings. They doubt not (I feare) to obtayne their ſcepters and crownes. They are for the forraine ennemy / and not for the upholding of France. Oh moſt dangerous Counſell / in ſo brave a Monarchie.</p>
            <p>Theſe good Fathers that outwardly ſeeme to be the true tipe and figure of Simplicitie / are inwardly ſtuffed with malice / and having ennemyes harts / can by no meanes procure the advancement of the ſtate / nor the good of the common welth of France: Their pernicious deſeigne is bent to the conſpiration of the totale ruin of this happie Monarchie; They ſeeke by the motions and ſterrings up of civill warres / which they goe about to make againſt us / by their peſtilent Preachers / to make a brech for our common ennemy that he maye ſoddenly enter into the midle of the preaſe / and deſireing nothing but his owne good diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſe our King of his Realme / pull him downe from his throane / and with us / bring him to the white bague.</p>
            <p>This is the end / this is the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / this is the deſeigne and attempt of theſe trayterous hipocrytes / of theſe Diveliſhe doble harts / of theſe perfidious and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyall Ieſuites / whoſe intents are not to ſet upon thoſe of the religion / to ſupport the Kings authoritie but to advance them ſelves / thoſe parricides / who with murthering armes / bathed their hands in the ſacred blood of our Kings / were they not either pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners / or ſchollers of the triple hornes / or were they not ſolicited and provoaked thereunto by their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſophiſtries / teaching / that it is a goodly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:9662:4"/>
to kill a King that is an hereticque / or that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voreth hereſie.</p>
            <p>If wee might be permitted to ſearch and looke into the regiſters of the depoſitions of the laſt deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate villaynes / wee ſhall finde that the laſt woordes of Ravaillac were theſe: ſaing / the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites promiſed and aſſured me / that as ſone as I had don the deed / the Angells and the Virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie woulde carrie mee into Parradiſe / and in truth / thoſe that were preſent at ſuch a woofull and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable accident / report / that as ſone as he hath ſtabd the King / he ſought to run awaye / thinking that / that which the Trecherous murtherers had ſayd would prove to be true / and wee ſhall not only know them by the laſt woords of that miſerable wretch / nor by the ſentence pronounced againſt them in their baniſhement / but by the cataſtrophall endes of all thoſe wicked perſons / which ſheweth them openlie to be infamous to poſteretie / and therefore they are ſo cruelly animated againſt us / bycauſe wee ſtrive againſt / and allwayes accuſe them of the death of our Kings; Therefore they ſeeke to rayſe warre againſt us / thinking thereby to root us out / but that is the thing which wee leaſt feare / proteſting theſe that firſt begin may perchance to repent it.</p>
            <p>Wee were promyſed that nothing ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novated in Bearn / to leave that buſines in ſuſpence and not to ſpeake of the 7. monthes / never the leſſe all thoſe promiſes were withdrawne / that dewe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings from ſuch perſons might be broaken / and his Majeſtie was perſwaded / and that by divers great perſonages / that it was a ſinne / yea and a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:9662:5"/>
great ſinne to hold his woord therein / and to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie that it is a worke of great pietie to violate his faith.</p>
            <p>Theſe whot ſpirits / theſe ſpotted and blacke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences / theſe diſguiſed Divells / theſe perfidious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernall Hogs / theſe Maſſacrers of Kings / publickely teach ſuch pernicious precepts / whereof the death of Chaſtel ſerveth for a witnes / and an authentike ſeale unto us. They were not content to have done a thouſand injuries unto us in Bearn / but ſince that tyme / (oh unſpeakeable crueltie / and furious mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) they have taken our deade bodies out of the earth / troubled their reſt / and uſed violence unto our carcaſes: ſeing it is a Huguenot / wee muſt pull him out of his grave / wee muſt tye a rope obout his necke and draw him through the ſtreets like a dog. Oh moſt outragious beaſtlynes and Diveliſhe furie.</p>
            <p>Theſe Barbarous cruelties were done unto us in the citie of <hi>Tours,</hi> and worſe then they / they brake downe our churche yeard / they defaced our Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and burnt it / and the Bible / the holy ſcriptures / the Goſpell and Teſtament of God. Whether doe theſe cruell vilaynes / ſuppoſe to triumphe againſt God / when they triumphe over his holy woord? and not content therewith / what have they not done? The repetition thereof is moſt lamentable.</p>
            <p>They animated ſedicious perſons in all places againſt us / they did us a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d miſchiefes / and yet (alas) wee durſt not open our mouthes to complayne thereof / that by our teares and ſightes wee might pacifie and aſſwge our greef. Some of our people were caſt in priſon / and ſome were glad to run away / 
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:9662:5"/>
and to ſet a faire ſhew upon their crueltie / they put ſome of their ſide likewiſe into priſon / that were ſhaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed awaye / and the matter winckt at. If wee had done the like / wee ſhould have bin impriſoned / hangd / and without forme of proceſſe wee ſhould hav bin puniſhed for an exemple unto others / (alas) will not a good counſell take order in ſo pitieful a diſtreſſe. My hart bleedes / but I dare not ſaye that which I know. <hi>Ne vati noceat eſſe locutum.</hi> A great tree in the ende is puld downe to the grownde / by pulling one peece this daye / an other that daye from it.</p>
            <p>Whie ſhould wee be blaſmed for aſſembling in Rochell / by the Kings permiſſion / they take this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to animate themſelves againſt us / to come the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to over run us / and to put all to fyer and ſword / wee are preſſed and perſwaded to ſeparate our ſelves which wee will never do. / that weare a meanes to begin againe / and to reduce us into the like miſerie. It muſt not be ſo / wee muſt either know the ſhort or the long / we have bin ſufficiently dalied withall / and in a manner afflicted / ſince the lamentable death of King Henrie the great of famous memorie / the more wee ſtaye / the more wee are vexed / the more wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit / the leſſe wee are eaſed.</p>
            <p>If they threathen to put us to death / wee are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed thereunto / if they threaten to burn us / wee have paſt through that allredy. If they threaten to cut of our heads / wee have tryed that alſo. Is not the river of Seine yet red all over with the blood of our Fathers? Is not the River of Loire all bloody by the meſure of our Bretheren? Is not the River
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:9662:6"/>
of Roſne yet purple with the blood of our graund-Fathers? Are not the aſhes of our prediceſſors that were burnt / ſtill whot? are not the high wayes ſtill full of the bones of our Kinſmen / that were trayte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly murthered? for the profeſſion of the reformed Religion? and for refuſeing to follow the footſtepp of Antechriſt? All this is nothing / let us make the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſhew of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ermilion color with the abondance of our blood / let us contemne fyer and fagot / ſwords and ſhot / gibet and wheel for Religion ſake / for the ſervice of God / and for profeſſing Ieſus Chriſt / for he himſelf ſaith: He that acknowledged me before men I will acknowledge him before my Father which is in Heaven / as to the contrarie / he ſaith to thoſe whome tribulation and feare of death hath made to fall from their profeſſion. He that ſhall denie me before Men / I will denie him before my Father which is in Heaven / he that is aſhamed to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge me before men / I will be aſhamed of him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my Father which is in Heaven: And againe / he that loveth his life more then me / is not worthy of me.</p>
            <p>They thinke by ſpoyling one member by deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one towne / by putting a thowſand Millions of people to death / that the whole body of Religion is thereby exterminated / wee ſpring up againe out of our aſhes / our blood hatcheth us againe. Thoſe great and cruell Maſſacres committed upon our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers / have not deminiſhed us. It is Gods cauſe / the Lord will undertake our defence / and withſtand the rage of our ennemyes.</p>
            <p>They make warre againſt us / which is manifeſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:9662:6"/>
and evident / but pietie is not the principal cauſe of their deſeigne / for ſeeing that Athiſts and Iewes are ſuffered to live peaceablie / they may wel permit us to live in the Realme indifferently among the common people obediently / as they have hetherto done / but bycauſe wee have directly banded our ſelves againſt the wicked enterpriſes of the ſatanicall inſtructions of this ſodometicall ſocietie / and that wee diſcloſe the ſubtilties / the craftines / the infernall practiſes / and the antitheticque or contrarie Doctrynes of this communaltie of mamon / and publiſhe and make them knowne to ſimple ignorant fellowes ſeducers of the people / they are ſtirred up againſt us feareing that their ſtate will dekie and wax worſe and worſe / and that in the ende they ſhall no longer be able to ſubſiſt againſt the truth / and alſo having an apre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion / that at the laſt they ſhall ſee the Romiſhe glorie and profit overthrowne / which to maintaine they doe moſt audaciouſly ſtrive againſt God / and bycauſe wee uphold his name and defend the truth / they ſeeke by a Diveliſhe counſell to deſtroy us / as the moſt ſtrong and moſt puiſant ennemyes of the apoſtolike ſeate.</p>
            <p>Theſe Dipers / theſe Baſilickes / theſe Tigers / theſe furious Dragons / are the cauſe of all the miſchief which wee ſee to be prepared generally to afflict all Frannce / ſpecially aiming at our deſtruction / like greedy and ravening Lyons. Let us ſtand firme and faſt by the tree of faith / and let us repoſe all our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fydence and hoape in Gsd / without looking or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending for ayde / from man / for / If God be with us / who ſhalbe againſt us?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:9662:7"/>Wee make profeſſion of the Reformed religion / let not / torments / martiring / rackes / nor horror of death make us at any time to waver / nor change our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: let us not feare the World / Emperors / Kings / Monarckes / Princes / nor whole realmes nor Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſediciouſly animated againſt us / let us freely and boldly confeſſe that wee are Chriſtians / and that wee will rather endure the crueltie of death / then denie Ieſus Chriſt. Nevertheleſſe let us flie and ſhun the occaſion / as much as wee can / and if wee can by no meanes avoyde the perill / and not hinder the blow / let us rather burſt then obay Antechriſt / let us rather embraſe condemnation then mercy / and ſhew our ſelves conſtant in death / for the Goſpell of Chriſt. God died for us / then are not wee bownd to die for him? Shall wee bowing downe our heades ſhamefuly without hoape / retire / eſteming our ſelves happie to have that favor and that libertie / after wee have bin proclaimed traitors to his Majeſtie?</p>
            <p>It is a follie / it muſt not be ſo / either wee will be puniſhed / or wee will be Iuſtified / wee will have all or nothing. Wee have ſet the crowne upon King Henry the fourth / deceaſed / of glorious memorie: (Fraunce knowes it well) and wee will give the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to King Lowis the 13. God will give that grace / being able to do more / and being ſtronger then wee are thought to be: awaye with favour / awaye with the mignions of fortune / and thoſe unmaried cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers / awaye with thoſe tapucine conſciences / they have ſufficientlie and to much / to our great greef / troubled the ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of our Atlas / by their bewitching ſorceries / poſſeſſing the nobleſt parts of his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:9662:7"/>Wee will not rebell againſt the King / and much leſſe will wee contradict the will of God / nor endure that men ſhould anihilate our auncient Priveledge / wee will not indure it / and let it not be thought to be ſtrange / if wee oppoſe the ſame withall our forces / for wee will never endure / that men ſhould put a knife to our throates / without putting their hands to it.</p>
            <p>If wee take Armes in hand / it ſhalbe to redſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhe the King upon his throane / to commaund ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely over his people / and to prevent that miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief / that is intended towards us / and if wee fight / to defend our ſelves / it ſhall bee to maintaine the faith of the Goſpell / and preſerve the Kings autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retie / although they cover themſelves with vaile of Regall authoritie / to aſſayle us / but al proceeds from wicked counſell. Wee feare God / and honor the King.</p>
            <p>What pitie is it? all the World is animatted ſore againſt us / and there are ſome amongſt us / that would betraie us / patience / let God be prayſed / and doe all for his glorie.</p>
            <p>At this daye it is a crime to be one of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion / but that crime is pleaſing unto God: There is neither Emperor / King / Monarche / Prince nor Lord / to be ſhort there is none / that wee ought to obaye before God. If they kill our bodyes / they can not kill our ſowles. They have a quarrell againſt us long ſince / all that formerly paſt / was but ſubtiletyes to intrap us / wee are put from publicque offices wee are prohibited common commerce / our Elections are tranſported / our Priviledges are eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:9662:8"/>
/ and if they durſt they would conſtraine us / to play banckcrupt with God / and religion / but wee will ſoner die then to doe wrong to our ſowles / wee will never doe it / yea rather die a thouſand deathes / then violate the Faith wee have vowed unto God. The three children conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned of Nabuchodonoſer and his fyer. The Prophet Daniel did not feare the rage of the Lyons / let us rather be kild / then bow our knies to Baal / let us rather be throwne into the mouthes of burning fyrie furnaſes then to breake our Law / and denie our God / and let us not loſe cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage / nor be afrayd / for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ll the traytors. Luke warne / and wicked men that m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>wnd among us / though they he never ſo great principall perſons / and puiſant / yea though they were our Fathers / Bretheren / Siſters / or our neereſt kinſmen. Ieſus Chriſt found a Iudas among his Apoſtles let us die / let us die couragiouſly to maintaine Gods quarrell / that at the ende of our courſe / after wee ſhall have fought a good fight he maye receave / and crowne us in Paradice / with the incorruptible crowne of glorie / perpetually to ſing to his honor and glorie with the Angels and the bleſſed for ever and ever / <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Veritas odium parit, &amp; Supplicium.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:9662:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
